Register of the Gleb Struve Papers 1810-1985
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1810-1985 (Boxes 69-148)
  - Sviatopolk-Mirskii, Prince Dimitrii
    - Bibliography of his works, typescript draft, n.d. (Box 139, Folder 1)
    - Tyrkova-Williams, Ariadna, review of Prince D. Sviatopolk-Mirskii, Russkaia Lirika, typescript draft, 1924 (Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous clippings and handwritten notes by Gleb Struve, 1972-1984 (Folder 3)
  - Tager, Elena
    - Correspondence. Excerpt from letter of Elena Tager to Iuliian Oksman, 1963 (Folder 4)
    - Biographical material
      - Anonymous, "Iz vospominanii ob E. M. Tager", typescript article, n.d. (Folder 5)
      - Struve, Gleb, biographical notes. Includes Elena Tager, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - Clippings. Includes clippings from Russkaia Mysl', 1965-1966 (Folder 7)
    - Writings
      - "Blok v 1915", Uchenye Zapiski Tartuskogo Gosudarstvennogo Universiteta, Tartu 1961. Includes introduction by Z. G. Mints (Folder 8)
      - "O Mandel'stame", Leningrad, 1962, typescript (Folder 9)
      - "Popad'ia", Zvezda, No. 12, 1928, photocopy (Folder 10)
      - Poetry, miscellaneous, typescripts and photocopies, 1943-1957 (Folder 11)
  - Tarsis, Valerii
    - Correspondence between Valerii Tarsis and Gleb Struve, 1966-1967 (Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous typescript material (Folder 13)
    - Clippings, 1956-1981 (Folder 14)
  - Teffi. Clippings, 1947-1985 (Folder 15)
  - Terapiano, Iurii
    - Correspondence between Iurii Terapiano and Gleb Struve, 1949-1979 (Folder 16)
    - Ivask, Iurii (?), biography, typescript, n.d. (Folder 17)
    - Clippings, 1947-1980 (Folder 18-19)
  - Tiutchev, Mikhail. Printed matter, 1976-1982 (Folder 20)
  - Tolstoy, Aleksei K.
    - Correspondence of Alexei Tolstoy
      - Gagarin, Aleksandr, 1861-1874. Holograph (photocopy). Original in Restricted Series (Box 140, Folder 1)
      - Katia, surname unknown, 1859?-1865. Holograph (photocopy). Original in Restricted Series (Folder 2)
      - Photocopies and typescripts of miscellaneous correspondence, 1864-1869. Also includes notes of Gleb Struve (Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1944-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Tolstoy, Lev
    - Scholarly articles, 1937-1982 (Folder 5)
    - Emigre newspapers, 1949-1983 (Folder 6)
  - Toporov, V. N.
    - Correspondence between V. N. Toporov and Gleb Struve, 1974-1980 (Folder 7)
    - Printed matter, tearsheets of scholarly articles, 1970 (Folder 8)
  - Trubetskoi, Grigorii. Writings, typescript excerpts from memoirs. Includes clippings of reviews of memoirs, 1983-1984 (Folder 9)
  - Trubetskoi, Iurii
    - Correspondence between Iurii Trubetskoi and Gleb Struve, 1953-1971 (Folder 10)
    - Clippings, 1935-1974 (Folder 11)
  - Tsurikov, Nikolai
    - Correspondence between Nikolai Tsurikov and Gleb Struve
      - 1924-May 1931 (Folder 12)
      - June-Dec. 1931 (Folder 13)
      - 1932-1938 (Folder 14)
      - 1939-1956 (Folder 15)
    - Writings
      - "Ideinaia otrava", typescript, n.d. (Box 141, Folder 1)
      - "Osnovy nashei neprimerimosti", 1948, printed copy of speech (Folder 2)
      - "Sovetskoe pravitel'stvo, inostrantsy, voina i pozitsiia emigratsii", Izdanie 'Vestnika O-va Gallipoliitsev", Sophia, 1936 (Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1932-1957. See also Rossiia i Slavianstvo, (La Russie et le Monde Slave) (Folder 4)
  - Tsvetaeva, Marina
    - Correspondence of Marina Tsvetaeva
      - Andronikova-Halpern, Salomeia. Photocopies
        - Undated (Folder 5)
        - 1926-1928 (Folder 6)
        - 1929-1930 (Folder 7)
        - 1931-1932. Includes letter of Ariadna Efron, 1932 (Folder 8)
        - 1933-1934 (Folder 9)
        - Typescripts of above (Folder 10)
      - Bunina, Vera. Holograph (photocopies). Originals in Restricted Series
        - 1928-1933 (Folder 11)
        - 1934-1937 (Folder 12)
        - Typescript excerpts from originals above, 1934-1935 (Folder 13)
      - Kantor, Mikhail, n.d. Photocopy. Original in Restricted Series (Folder 14)
      - Sviatopolk-Mirskii, Dimitrii, 1925-1926, photocopies (Folder 15)
      - Pasternak, Boris
        - 1922-1927. Photocopies of typescripts. Received from Vadim Morkovin, Prague, 1968 (Folder 16)
        - 1922-1928. Photocopies with introduction and commentaries by Gleb Struve, n.d. (Folder 17)
        - 1923. Photocopy of typescript with introduction by Viktoria Schweitzer, n.d. (Folder 18)
      - Struve, Gleb, 1923-1925. Holograph (photocopies). Originals in Restricted Series (Folder 19)
      - Struve, Iuliia, 1923. Holograph (photocopies). Originals in Restricted Series (Folder 20)
    - General, photocopies and typescripts, 1925-1983 (Folder 21)
    - Correspondence of Gleb Struve re Marina Tsvetaeva
      - Eleneva, E., 1957-1958 (Folder 22)
      - Morkovina, M., 1973 (Folder 23)
    - Writings
      - Poetry
        - Single sheets, n.d. Includes excerpts from "Lebedinyi stan", holograph (photocopy). Originals in Restricted Series (Folder 24)
        - Clippings, Russian and in translation, 1967-1983 (Folder 25)
        - Photocopies
          - "Lebedinyi stan", photocopy of manuscript in the University of Basel Archive, 1917-1921 (Folder 26)
          - "Perekop", 1926, same as above (Folder 27)
        - Miscellaneous, typescripts and photocopies, 1913-1941 (Box 142, Folder 1-2)
      - Prose
        - "Dva lesnykh tsaria",typescript, 1933 (Folder 3)
        - "Tvoia smert'", Bellevue, 1927, typescript (Folder 4)
        - "Staryi Pimen", Clamart, 1933. Holograph (photocopy). Original in Restricted Series (Folder 5)
        - "U starogo Pimena", typescript copy. See also correspondence between Gleb Struve and L. Zurov (Folder 6)
        - Photocopies of miscellaneous published prose and correspondence (Folder 7)
    - Biographical material
      - Efron, Ariadna, "Stranitsy bylogo", Zvezda, 1975, photocopy (Folder 8)
      - Footnotes for correspondence of Marina Tsvetaeva prepared by Gleb Struve for Marina Tsvetaeva. Neizdannye Pis'ma, Y.M.C.A. Press, Paris, 1972 (Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous typescript material, 1937-1960 (Folder 10)
    - Critical material
      - Articles, typescript, n.d.
        - Kemball, Robin. Miscellaneous material re Marina Tsvetaeva (Folder 11)
        - Schweitzer, Viktoria. "Bratskaia mogila" (Folder 12)
        - Smith, G. S., "Marina Tsvetaeva: Additions to the Canon" and "Marina Tsvetaeva and D. S. Mirsky" (Folder 13)
        - Gorodetskii, Sergei, "Zhenskoe Rukodelie", Rech', Apr. 30, 1912 (Folder 14)
        - Khodasevich, Vladislav, Vozrozhdenie, June 19, 1928 (Folder 15)
      - Printed matter
        - Articles from scholarly journals, photocopies and reprints, 1923-1982 (Folder 16)
        - Book reviews of works re Marina Tsvetaeva, 1962-1983 (Folder 17)
        - Clippings, 1925-1984 (Folder 18-19)
    - "Moskovskaia gorodskaia organizatsiia dobrovol'nogo obshchestva liubitelei knigi RSFSR ... Khronoka 25 tematicheskikh vstrech, posviashchennykh zhizni i tvorchestvu Mariny Ivanovny Tsvetaevoi", 1978-1985, photocopy (Folder 20)
    - Symposium, Lausanne, miscellaneous material, 1982 (Box 143, Folder 1)
    - Lists of published poetry and prose composed by Gleb Struve (Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous typescript material, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - Tuck, Robert
    - Correspodence between Robert Tuck and Gleb Struve, 1967 (Folder 4)
    - "Influencing Political Change By Broadcasting to the Soviet Union", speech delivered at the 1966 annual meeting of The American Political Science Association (Folder 5)
  - Turgenev, Aleksandr Ivanovich
    - Correspondence. Typescript copies of printed material and handwritten notes by Gleb Struve, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - Anonymous, "A. N. Turgenev i ego sem'ia", typescript draft, n.d. (Folder 7)
    - Struve, Gleb, miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - Printed matter. Clippings from scholarly journals, 1899-1967 (Folder 9)
  - Turgenev, Ivan
    - Biographical material. Semenoff, E., "La vie douloureuse d'Ivan Tourgeneff", Mercure de la France, section I, IV,VIII, Nov. 15, 1931-June 1, 1932 (Folder 10)
    - Printed matter
      - Scholarly articles, 1966-1984 (Folder 11)
      - Clippings from emigre newspapers, 1944-1983 (Folder 12)
  - Tvardovskii, Aleksandr. Clippings, 1945-1985 (Folder 13)
  - Tvorchestvo, June 1918, printed copy (Folder 14)
  - Ul'ianov, Nikolai. Clippings, 1959-1978 (Folder 15)
  - Vagin, Evgenii. Clippings, 1980-1981 (Folder 16)
  - Valentinov, Nikolai, see Vol'skii, Nikolai
  - Vestnik krest'ianskoi Rossii, June-July 1931-Feb. 1932 (Folder 17)
  - Vestnik RSKhD. Clippings, 1927-1984 (Folder 18)
  - Viazemskii, Prince Petr
    - Letters to unidentified correspondent, 1866-1876 (?). Holograph (photocopies). Originals in Restricted Series (Folder 19)
    - Writings
      - "Sovremennyia zametki", 1854. Holograph (photocopy). Original in Restricted Series (Folder 20)
      - Bound notebook including miscellaneous printed matter by and about Prince Peter Viazemskii
        - "Pervyi sneg", 1817 (Folder 21)
        - Sviataia rus', Sankpeterburg, 1848 (Folder 22)
        - Pesn' na den' rozhdeniia V. A. Zhukovskago, 29-go Ianvaria 1849 (Folder 23)
        - Obed dannyi v Moskve, Oktiabria 21-go dnia, v chest' kniazia P. A. Viazemskago, 1850 (Folder 24)
        - Piat' stikhotvorenii kniazia P. A. Viazemskago, 1958 (Folder 25)
        - Shest' stikhotvorenii, kn. Viazemskago, 1855 (Folder 26)
        - Stikhotvorenie kn. Viazemskago, 1856 (Folder 27)
        - Za granitseiu, korrekturnye listy, 1859 (Folder 28)
        - Grafu Dmitriiu Nikolaevichu Bludovu, 8-go Ianvaria 1851 goda, holograph (?) (Folder 29)
        - Osviashchenie novosooruzhennoi nadgrobnoi Eia Imperatorskago Vysochestva Gosudaryni Velikoi Kniagini Elizavety Mikhailovny, 1855 (Folder 30)
        - Pis'mo V. A. Zhukovskago k kniaziu P. A. Viazemskomu, n.d. (Folder 31)
    - Gleb Struve, miscellaneous handwritten notes, n.d. (Folder 32)
  - Vinogradov, Igor'. Clippings, 1976-1984 (Box 144, Folder 1)
  - Vishniak, Mark
    - Correspondence between Mark Vishniak and Gleb Struve
      - 1945-1962 (Folder 2)
      - 1963-1973 (Folder 3)
    - Writings
      - Lenin's Democracy and Stalin's, printed copy, 1946 (Folder 4)
      - "Pravo ubezhishcha", galley proof and offprint, 1955 (Folder 5)
      - Untitled typescript, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - Struve, Gleb, miscellaneous notes and typescript excerpts from Mark Vishniak's archive, 1927-1931 (Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1947-1976 (Folder 8)
  - Voinovich, Vladimir. Clippings, 1982-1985 (Folder 9)
  - Voloshin, Maksimilian
    - Correspondence of Gleb Struve about Voloshin, 1965-1979 (Folder 10)
    - Writings
      - "Avtobiografiia", photocopy of typescript, 1925 (Folder 11)
      - Anno Mundis Ardentes, 1915, Izdatel'stvo "Zerna", Moscow 1916, photocopy (Folder 12)
      - Stikhotvoreniia MCM-MCMX. Gody stranstvii. Amori amara sacrum. Zvezda polyn'. Altari. V pustyne. Corona astralis. k-vo Grife, photocopy of printed work (Folder 13)
      - "Vliublennyi d'iavol", draft of scenario, typescript, n.d. (Folder 14)
      - "Vospominaniia o Cherubine de Gabriiak", typescript, n.d. (Folder 15)
      - Miscellaneous poetry, typescript and clippings, 1922-1951 (Folder 16)
    - Critical material
      - Avinova, M., "Vstrecha s Maksimilianom Voloshinym", typescript draft, n.d. (Box 145, Folder 1)
      - Russov, Aleksei, "Poeziia Maksimiliana Voloshina", typescript draft, 1947 (Folder 2)
    - Clippings. Includes biographical material and memoirs, 1932-1985 (Folder 3)
  - Vol'skii, Nikolai
    - Correspondence between Valentinov-Vol'skii and Gleb Struve, 1954-1961 (Folder 4)
    - Writings
      - Drafts, typescript, n.d.
        - "Blok i 'Russkoe Slovo'" (Folder 5)
        - "Dva goda sredi simvolistov" (Folder 6)
        - "Evropeizm i russkie polia" (Folder 7)
        - Untitled writing, relates to "Vekhi" (Folder 8)
      - Clippings of his newspaper articles, 1952-1970 (Folder 9)
    - Aronson, Grigorii, "Nikolai Vol'skii" (obituary), Novoye Russkoye Slovo, Oct. 2, 1964 (Folder 10)
  - Vorontsov, Count Simon
    - Correspondence related to Gleb Struve's work on Vorontsov, 1945-1957 (Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous research material and notes compiled by Gleb Struve. Includes typescript excerpts of correspondence, n.d. (Folder 12-13)
  - Vozrozhdenie
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1927 (Box 146, Folder 1)
      - Struve, Gleb, 1969-1973 (Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous clippings including anniversary issues with photographs of staff and contributors, 1927-1935 (Folder 3)
  - Weidle, Vladimir
    - Correspondence between Vladimir Weidle and Gleb Struve, 1935-1979 (Folder 4)
    - Writings, "Peterburgskaia poetika", typescript draft, n.d. (Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1927-1976 (Folder 6-7)
  - Yakobson, Roman
    - Correspondence between Roman Yakobson and Gleb Struve, 1948-1968 (Folder 8)
    - Obituaries, printed copies, 1984 (Folder 9)
  - Zabelin, Ivan. Dva iubileiia ucheno-literaturnoi i sluzhebnoi deiatel'nosti Ivana Egorovicha Zabelina, 1910 (Folder 10)
  - Zabolotskii, Nikolai. Miscellaneous typescript material, n.d. (Folder 11)
  - Zaitsev, Boris
    - Correspondence between Boris Zaitsev and Gleb Struve, 1933-1971 (Folder 12)
    - Clippings, 1926-1972 (Folder 13)
  - Zaitsev, Kirill
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1925-1926 (Folder 14)
      - Amfiteatrov, A., 1920-1926 (Folder 15)
      - Chelishchev, V.N., 1925 (Folder 16)
      - Davats, V. KH., 1925 (Folder 17)
      - Elenev, N. A., 1925-1926 (Folder 18)
      - Gornyi, S. (Otsup), 1925 (Box 147, Folder 1)
      - Hoeffding, W. (Geffding, V.), 1925-1926 (Folder 2)
      - Kuprin, A., n.d. (Folder 3)
      - Lazarevskii, B. A., 1925-1926 (Folder 4)
      - Makovskii, S. K., 1925-1926 (Folder 5)
      - Mukshtein, L., n.d. (Folder 6)
      - Shul'gin, Vasilii, 1925 (Folder 7)
      - Struve, Gleb, 1924-1956 (Folder 8)
      - Struve, Petr B., 1925-1928, typescript copies (Folder 9)
      - Teffi, N., n.d. (Folder 10)
      - Tsurikov, N. A., 1925 (Folder 11)
      - Varshavskii, V.S., n.d. (Folder 12)
    - Writings
      - "Le regime du servage agraire en Russie avant la reforme de 1861", typescript with holograph annotations, 1932 (Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1931 (Folder 14)
  - Zamiatin, Evgenii
    - Correspondence of Gleb Struve
      - General. Includes correspondence re publication of Zamiatin's We, 1946-1947 (Folder 15)
      - Zamiatina, Liudmila, 1946-1955 (Folder 16)
    - Clippings, 1932-1983
    - Writings
      - Autobiographical sketch, Rul', April 9, 1922, typescript copy (Folder 17)
      - Obituary of Anatole France in Russkii Sovremennik, Typescript copy, 1924 (Folder 18)
      - "The Nursery", translated by R. Norman typescript, n.d. (Folder 19)
      - Short stories, typescript copies, n.d. Includes "Chekhov", "M. Gorkii", "Morbus Russica", "Vospominaniia o Bloke", "Vstechi s B. M. Kustodievym", "Zontik" (Folder 20)
      - Synopsis of film scenario for the novel We, n.d. (Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous material. Includes photocopies of articles re Zamiatin, 1966-1976 (Folder 22)
    - Clippings, 1937-1973 (Folder 23)
    - See also correspondence of Gleb Struve and George Orwell
  - Zapiski nabliudatelia. Literaturnyi sbornik, printed copy, 1924. Restricted Series (Folder 24-26)
  - Zavalishin, Viacheslav. Clippings, 1958-1983 (Folder 27)
  - Zavalishin, Viacheslav. Clippings, 1958-1983 (Box 148, Folder 1-3)
  - Zinoviev, Kirill. Clippings, 1980-1984 (Folder 4)
  - Znamia, 1921, printed copy (Folder 5)
  - Zoshchenko, Mikhail
    - Miscellaneous typescript material, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - Clippings, 1956-1983 (Folder 7)
  - Zurov, Leonid
    - Correspondence between Leonid Zurov and Gleb Struve, 1935-1971 (Folder 8)
    - Excerpts from reviews of his book, typescript, 1928-1949 (Folder 9)
- COURSE MATERIAL, 1933-1968 (Boxes 148-150)
  Miscellaneous material related to courses taught by Gleb Struve. Includes notes used in preparing the course, reading lists, class handouts and examinations. Arranged by subject.
  - University of London. Lectures, 1933-1934
    - Notes (Box 148, Folder 10)
    - Typescript drafts (Folder 11)
  - Dostoevsky, Fedor, Notebook I and II, holograph, 1937 (Folder 12)
  - Leontiev, Konstantin, handwritten and typescript drafts, 1933 (Folder 13)
  - B.A. examinations for honors, printed copies, 1939-1946 (Folder 14)
  - Harvard University
    - "Russian Literature Outside Russia", typescript copies of lectures, n.d. (Box 149, Folder 1)
    - "Recent Developments in Soviet Literature", seminar notes, Russian Research Center, Harvard University, typescript copy, 1968 (Folder 2)
  - University of California, Berkeley
    - "The Nature of Culture", Anthropology 118A, typescript and handwritten notes, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - "19th Century Russian Literature", Slavic 130, typescript notes, n.d. (Folder 4)
    - "Recent Russian Literature", Slavic 131, typescript notes, n.d. (Folder 5)
    - "Russian Literature Since 1917", Slavic 132, typescript notes, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - "Russian Literature and Folklore", Slavic 134, typescript notes, n.d. (Folder 7)
    - "Modern Russia", Slavic 138, typescript notes, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - "Polish Romantic Poetry", Slavic 152, typescript and hanwritten notes, n.d. (Folder 9)
    - "Dostoevskij in Literary Criticism and Scholarship", Slavic 290Q, typescript bibliographies, n.d. (Folder 10)
    - "Gogol' in Russian Literary Criticism", miscellaneous course material, typescript, n.d. (Folder 11)
    - "Russian Versification", Slavic 187, miscellaneous typescript material, 1961 (Folder 12)
    - "Studies in Early Soviet Prose", Slavic 290 reading list, typescript copy, n.d. 1950's?) (Folder 13)
    - Student recommendations and examination reports, typescript copies, 1949 (Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous typescript bibliographies, n.d. (Folder 15)
    - Unsorted typescript and holograph notes, n.d. (Folder 16)
    - Unsorted typescript and holograph notes, n.d. (Box 150, Folder 1-2)
- RESTRICTED SERIES, 1810-1957, Originals (in Boxes 151-153) may be viewed under supervision only. Use copies (in Boxes 185-187) are available (Boxes 151-153, 185-187)
  Holograph and fragile material (in Boxes 151-153), arranged by subject, may be viewed under supervision only. Use copies (in Boxes 185-187) are available
  - Anrep, Boris. Untitled poems dedicated to Anna Akhmatova, holograph, n.d. (Box 151, Folder 1)
  - Gumilev, Nikolai
    - Personal documents
      - Military Service Record, (posluzhnoi spisok), Dec. 1916 (Folder 2)
      - Certificate no. 2082. Payments made by Quartermaster General of the Russian Expeditionary Force in France to Nikolai Gumilev, Paris, Jan. 1918 (Folder 3)
      - "Memoire concernant la possibilite eventuelle d'un recrutement de contingents de volontaires pour l'Armee Francaise en Abyssinie", holograph, n.d. (Folder 4)
      - Letter from Gumilev to Representative of Provisional Government requesting transfer to Persian Front, Jan 1918, holograph (Folder 5)
      - Documents relating to Gumilev's mission to London
        - Official order for mission
          - Jan. 3/16, 1918, in Russian (Folder 6)
          - Jan. 20, 1918, in French (Folder 7)
        - Certificate of payment of salary and travel expenses. Stamped "Attache Militaire de Russie a Londres", Jan. 1918 (Folder 8)
        - Russian Military Agent in Great Britain
          - Letter informing Gumilev of arrival of correspondence from Paris, Feb. 5/Jan. 23, 1918 (Folder 9)
          - Official request for personal information, signed Balashov, Feb. 21, 1918 (Folder 10)
        - Notebook containing notes, addresses, appointments, 1918, holograph (Folder 11)
        - Bill from Turner's Hotel, April, 1918 (Folder 12)
    - Writings
      - Poetry
        - "Mik i Lui", Niva, No. 4, Feb. 1917, galley proof (Folder 13)
        - Otravlennaia tunika
          - "Tragediia v piati deistviiakh", Paris, London, Spring 1917, Winter, 1918, holograph (Folder 14)
          - Beginning of fair copy, holograph, n.d. (Folder 15)
          - Stage directions and miscellaneous single sheets, holograph, n.d. (Folder 16)
        - Notebook containing 4 poems in French, holograph, n.d. (Folder 17)
        - "Sentimental'noe stikhotvorenie dlia T. M. Devich", 1905, holograph (Folder 18)
        - "Stikhi". Notebook containing c. 80 poems. Illustrated by Dimitrii Stelletski and Natalia Goncharova, 1916, holograph (Folder 19)
      - Prose
        - "Veselye brat'ia"
          - Beginning of fair copy, holograph, n.d. (Box 152, Folder 1)
          - Miscellaneous single sheets, holograph, n.d. (Folder 2)
        - Miscellaneous single sheets, n.d. (Folder 3)
      - Drawings
        - Cocteau, Jean (?). Small portrait in ink of Pablo Picasso. Sent by Cocteau to Gumilev in Paris, 1916 (Folder 4)
        - Gumilev, Nikolai. Two small pencil drawings, n.d. (Folder 5)
        - Larionov, Mikhail. Two small pencil portraits of Gumilev in uniform, n.d. (Folder 6)
        - Stelletski, Dimitrii. Self-portrait (?) Drawing in ink with autograph, n.d. (Folder 7)
    - Kozlovskii, Prince Petr. Writings
      - Letter from Prince Petr Kozlovskii to Count Romantsov, 1810 (Folder 8)
      - Letter from Prince (?) Varshavskii to Prince Petr Kozlovskii, 1839 (Folder 9)
    - Nedobrovo, Nikolai
      - Correspondence between Nikolai Nedobrovo and Boris Anrep, 1910-1914 (Folder 10)
      - Writings. Leatherbound book of poetry, holograph, 1904 (Folder 11)
    - Remizov, Aleksei
      - Correspondence between Aleksei Remizov and Gleb Struve, 1923-1957 (Folder 12)
      - Writing. "O besnovatoi Solomonii", printed copy with holograph introduction, Paris, 1929 (Folder 13)
    - Rozanov, Vasilii. Correspondence between Vasilii Rozanov and Zinaida Gippius, 1906-1907 (Box 153, Folder 1)
    - Tolstoy, Aleksei. Correspondence
      - Gagarin, Prince Aleksandr, 1861-1874 (Folder 2)
      - Katia, surname unknown, 1859(?)-1865 (Folder 3)
    - Tsvetaeva, Marina
      - Correspondence
        - Bunina, Vera, 1928-1937 (Folder 4)
        - Kantor, Mikhail, n.d. (Folder 5)
        - Struve, Gleb, 1923-1925 (Folder 6)
        - Struve, Iulia, 1923 (Folder 7)
      - Writings
        - "U starogo Pimena", Clamart, 1933 (Folder 8)
        - Single sheets. Includes excerpts from "Lebedinyi stan", n.d. (Folder 9)
    - Viazemskii, Prince Petr
      - Letters to unidentified correspondent, 1866-1876(?) (Folder 10)
      - Writings
        - "Sovremennyia zametki", 1854, holograph (Folder 11)
        - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1847-1859 (Folder 12)
    - Zapiski Nabliudatelia, Literaturnyi Sbornik, Prague, 1924, printed copy (Folder 13)
- VISUAL MATERIALS, 1890's-1985 (Box 154)
  Prints, drawings, and painting, arranged by subject.
  - Prints, drawings, and painting (Box 154)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1905-1971 (Box 155)
  Oversize miscellany, arranged by subject.
  - Albums (Box 155)
    - Album of Struve family photographs., 1890's-1940's (Folder 155)
      Includes prints of Struve family ancestral portraits, prints of Peter Struve, his wife and sons.
    - Album of photographs taken at professional conferences attended by Gleb Struve., 1951-1977 (Folder 155)
    - Clippings of articles by Gleb Struve, 1950-1959
  - Honorary Degree from University of Toronto, 1971
- MEMORABILIA
  - Epaulettes from military uniform of Nikolai Gumilev (Box 156)
- INDEX CARD FILE, n.d. (Boxes 157-181)
  Index card notes by Gleb Struve, mostly relating to Russian literature. Includes miscellaneous bibliographies. Unsorted.
  - Unsorted index cards, n.d. (Box 157-181)
- CLIPPINGS, 1930's-1980's. (Boxes 182-183)
  - Material re Russian art, music, literature, and history, including pre-Revolutionary, Soviet and emigre periods. Also includes correspondence of Peter Soskice (Box 182-183)
- CORRESPONDENCE, CHRONOLOGICAL, 1931-1950
  - Miscellaneous letters (Box 183)
- CORRESPONDENCE, ALPHABETICAL, 1965-1985
  - General, 1965-1981 (Box 184, Folder 1)